<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The heart of the king, and the king of the heart, or, A briefe vnfolding of that remarkable proverbe of the royall preacher ... written in the time of His Maiesties abode at Plimmouth, and preferred vnto him in his returne from thence, anno 1625 : together with a short meditation vpon 2. Sam. 24.15., preached at a weekely lecture in Deuon, in those fearefull times of mortalitie / by J.P. Master of Arts and minister of the gospell.</title>
            <author>Pyne, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20521.8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4427</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24386740</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24386740</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27611</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10242)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27611)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1823:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The heart of the king, and the king of the heart, or, A briefe vnfolding of that remarkable proverbe of the royall preacher ... written in the time of His Maiesties abode at Plimmouth, and preferred vnto him in his returne from thence, anno 1625 : together with a short meditation vpon 2. Sam. 24.15., preached at a weekely lecture in Deuon, in those fearefull times of mortalitie / by J.P. Master of Arts and minister of the gospell.</title>
                  <author>Pyne, John.</author>
                  <author>J. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A briefe meditation vpon the fifteenth verse of the twenty      fourth chapter of the second booke of Samuel" has special t.p. dated 1626.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Pyne by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2] at beginning.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXI, 1 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, XXIV, 15 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>The Heart of the King; and the King of the Heart. OR A briefe vnfolding of that remarkable PROVERBE of the Royall PREACHER.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>PROVERB. 21.1.</bibl>
                     <p>The Kings Heart is in the hand of the <hi>LORD.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Written in the time of his Maieſties abode at <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> and preferred vnto him in his returne from thence. ANNO 1625.</p>
                  <p>Together with a ſhort Meditation vpon 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.15.</p>
                  <p>Preached at a Weekely Lecture in <hi>Deuon:</hi> in thoſe fearefull times of <hi>MOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TALITIE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. P.</hi> Maſter of Arts and Miniſter of the GOSPELL.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby,</hi> 1628.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:2"/>
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>PAg. 10. line 13. read, <hi>their hearts.</hi> pag. 12. l. 29. r. <hi>King.</hi> p. 32. l. 2. r. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 12. p. 51. l. 2. r. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab.</hi> p. 55. l. 15. r. <hi>depriue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE <hi>PRINCE</hi> CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD King of Great <hi>Brittaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt gracious Soueraigne,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T might iuſtly bee cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as an intolerable raſhneſſe in your vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Subiect, that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo lately pardoned for his great audaciouſneſſe, ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:27611:3"/>
yet againe preſume in the ſame kind; had he not read charactered in your very countenance, <hi>Quanto maior tanto melior,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Quanto melior tanto mitior,</hi> that your Sonereigne Greatneſſe made way for your boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Goodneſſe, and boundles Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes; and beene confident that it would graciouſly conſider, that albeit it were an vnwonted preſumption for ſo meane a Subiect to aduance in ſo ſhort a ſpace, to ſo high a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, two ſeuerall paper-preſents (as vnworthy to be read, as euery way vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie) yet the rare preſence of ſo great an Highneſſe as the eldeſt eye hath not ſeene in theſe parts of your Dominions, (which are not ſo farre diſtant from your Royall Manſions, as their people are neerely linked to
<pb facs="tcp:27611:3"/>
the ſeruice of your Maieſtie) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that great and generall emulation of your loyall Subiects, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to doe your Maieſtie ſome accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruice in this vnuſuall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, might be admitted to mediate vnto your Royall fauour for a renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the former Pardon, and giuing acceptance to the ſame perſon, who with as much loyall reſpect as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with the ſame proſtrate humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie deuoteth this his ſecond ſeruice to your ſacred ſelfe, in your Princely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from the period of your long progreſſe; humbly deſiring the Lord of Hoaſts to proſper your Maieſties Royall <hi>Marriage, Leagues, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies, Armies</hi> and <hi>Iourneyes,</hi> that they may tend to the Glorie of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie,</hi> the terror of your Enemies,
<pb facs="tcp:27611:4"/>
the aſſurance of your ſafetie, the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours of your deiected Siſter, and the comfort of your deuoted Subiects, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst whom, euen in that long <hi>Roll</hi> extended in the Weſterne <hi>Chart,</hi> there ſhall euer be found while life ſhall remayne,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Maieſties moſt loyall and obedient Subiect, <hi>J. P.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27611:4"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>PROV. 21.1.</bibl>
                        <p>The Kings Heart is in the hand of the <hi>LORD.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is written in the hearts of all men by the hand of the ALMIGHTIE, that wherſoeuer they are <hi>Hee is preſent with them, and acquainted with all their wayes, Pſal.</hi> 139.3. And yet thoſe Books of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord laid vp in the breſts of the Reprobate are ſo blotted and ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſinne, that they can hardly reade Gods preſence in them, and much leſſe conſtrue it aright. Therefore hee is pleaſed to manifeſt himſelfe in the hearts of his Elect, in a fairer Character of a more gracious and propitious preſence, and that moſt ſpecially when they are aſſembled in his Name, and in his Houſe,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27611:5"/>
Hee then promiſing that although they bee but two or three, yet he will be nigh them, yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and amidſt them too, not only in the Bodie of his Temple, but in the very Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of their Bodies, in his Houſe, and in their hearts. <hi>Prope Deus est, cum ijs est, in ijs. Inter eos &amp; intra eos: With them and within them.</hi> But to come neerer. Amongſt all the choſen hearts of Gods Seruants, God reſerueth his choiſeſt preſence for the hearts of his choſen and anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Seruants;<note place="margin">The royall heart is Gods great Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.</note> And amongſt all godly Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, hee is pleaſed to take vp his ſpeciall <hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Congregation of Gods,</hi> where Kings and Princes meet to doe him ſeruice, and to call vpon his Name, by whoſe Name they are called. <hi>Bethel</hi> rhe Kings Chappell is moſt ſignificantly the Houſe of God, and queſtionleſſe, God will be moſt peculiarly preſent with the Kings heart; for behold in this Text he hath giuen his <hi>Word,</hi> and his <hi>Hand</hi> for it,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Heart of the King is in the hand of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the hand of the Lord is the heart of euery liuing Creature, it being the principall part of that admired workmanſhip of his owne diuine hand; but ſpecially the heart of man the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Creature, who is the ſpeciall Maſter-piece of his workmanſhip, as bearing his owne Image, and yet more peculiarly the heart of the King the principall man, who is more peculiarly his Image, as being his owne Vicegerent. <hi>The Kings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27611:5"/>
Heart is in the hand of the LORD.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we take the heart at the Lords hand, as he vouchſafeth to take it at ours, <hi>viz.</hi> for the whole liuing creature, Behold his hand is ouer all his workes, it filleth all things liuing with plentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it feedeth and ſaueth both Man and Beaſt; <hi>In his hands are all the corners of the</hi> EARTH, as well as all the corners of the HEART, as the Pſalmiſt teacheth. <hi>In his hand,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, is the ſoule of euery liuing thing, and the breath of all Mankind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in this generall ſubordination and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection what will bee the prerogatiue of man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other Creatures, or of Kings aboue other men? Certainly much. The inferiour creatures are in the hand of God, yet ſo that hee hath alſo put them into the hands of men,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28.</note> and they haue dominion ouer them; Inferiour men are in the hand of God, yet ſo that he hath alſo deliuered them into the hands of Kings, and <hi>they exerciſe authoritie vpon them.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25:</note> But as for Kings ſhall I ſay that they only are abſolutely in Gods hands; I may ſay abſolutely that they are in Gods hands only. God hath put the liues of others into their hands, them hee hath reſerued for his owne. <hi>The Kings Heart is in the hand of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was not only <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe who was a man after Gods owne heart, and had ſo ſweete an experimentall knowledge of Gods gracious tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Nor <hi>Salomons</hi> alone who had ſo faithfull
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27611:6"/>
an aſſurance of Gods fauourable aſſiſtance, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on ſo full a promiſe, as that God would be his Father, and he ſhould bee his Child, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with ſo faire a pawne as the fulneſſe of wiſdome and an vnderſtanding heart: This is a caſe common to Kings, and muſt bee pleaded by a Prouerbe, <hi>The Kings Heart is in the hand of the Lord:</hi> A Prouerbe that carrieth with it power and authoritie, pith and ſignificancie, wherein yee haue the <hi>hand of the Lord,</hi> and the very <hi>heart of the King, Manum diuinam, Mentem regiam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Summus vtri<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Martial.</note>Autor adest, haec eſt Caeſaris, illa Dei.</l>
                     <l>The Kings Heart is in the hand of the Lord.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 14.10.</note>But, what hath God an hand? <hi>Is God alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come weake as we, is he become like vnto vs.</hi> It is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall with vs, as to chriſten diuers men, ſo to call different things by one and the ſame name: <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem &amp; noſtrum dicimus &amp; lecti &amp; veli &amp; carmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> ſaith that ſage Heathen: Our weakneſſe is the ſtrongeſt reaſon for it that hee ſtandeth on, <hi>Quia non ſufficimus vt ſingula ſingulis aſsignemus.</hi> So ſtandeth the caſe with vs men, it is nothing ſo with God. Hath he a foot? it is to ſupport our infirmities: it is to tread a path for our capacities. Hath he an Hand in my Text? it is to direct our decayed knowledge; it is to lead our blind vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings. If any therefore ſhall make a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion how the hand may bee faſtened on God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27611:6"/>
with whom things corporall can hold no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, The Figure <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> muſt ſhape him an anſwere, by which our great God mercifully deſcending and condeſcending vnto our meane capacities, doth, becauſe we cannot vnderſtand him in the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſpeake vnto vs in our owne Mother-tongue, and becauſe wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reade the diuine Characters of his Eſſence, and Preſence, writeth in our owne hand; <hi>The Kings Heart is in the hand of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this hand then God leadeth vs to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of that high eſteeme which hee vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth vs, as if it were not enough for vs that he had made vs like himſelfe, Hee would, if it were poſſible, make himſelfe like vs. But heere (to ſpeake more pertinently) God eſpecially beareth vs in hand, <hi>Quam habiturus ſit circa publicas perſonas ſpecialem prouidentiam:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Carthuſ.</note> What an high regard he will haue of Royall ſublimitie. As if it were not enough for Kings that the Hoaſt of the Lord were their Guard, the Lord of Hoaſts will bee their Guardian: his hand ſhall mayntaine their right and manage their affaires. <hi>The Kings Heart is in the hand of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will not diuide or diuorce the <hi>Lords hand</hi> from the <hi>Kings heart: What God hath coupled I will not put aſunder.</hi> Let hand and heart goe together. In the ioynture it ſhall bee ſufficient for mee to handle.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Gods royall Prerogatiue ouer the Heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Gods Prerogatiue ouer the Heart royall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:27611:7"/>The firſt of theſe will euidence that God car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth an hand ouer the hearts of all men in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond, that he hath an eſpeciall hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the hearts of Kings.</p>
                  <p>And theſe are the generall obſeruations.</p>
                  <p>Gods prerogatiue ouer the heart conſiſteth principally in the diſquiſition, and in the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof, in ſearching and in turning it: the former exerciſed as well in the Reprobate as the Elect, the other in the Elect only: Both moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently in Kings and men of the higheſt ranke.</p>
                  <p>That it is Gods prerogatiue to ſearch the heart will ſoone appeare,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.21.</note> vpon a ſearch of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: <hi>Shall not God ſearch this out, for he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſecrets of the heart,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> The heart is the fountaine of life; <hi>with God is the fountaine of life,</hi> to vſe in this ſenſe the ſaying of the ſame Kingly Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. <hi>This Well is deepe and we haue nothing wherewith to draw. Our owne hearts are deceitfull;</hi> we can hardly euer find the depth of our owne, much leſſe ſound the Bottome of anothers heart. Yea, but <hi>ex abundantia cordis os lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur,</hi> the words which a man letteth fall,<note place="margin">By the ſpeech as by the pulſe we may gheſſe at the temper of the heart.</note> the threed of his ſpeech like that of <hi>Ariadne's</hi> Clue, may ſomewhat direct vs in tracing the Maze, and following the turnings and windings of the heart. When I heare a mouth breathing out ſcurrilitie and blaſphemies, a mouth vnder whoſe roofe God and good men neuer come, but they receiue a wound; what ſhall I ſay, but that it is retayner
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27611:7"/>
and reporter to a wicked heart. Thus might wee iudge of the temper of the heart in generall, but muſt leaue the exact ſearch to the hand of the Lord. We may yet be much miſtaken and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſome externall <hi>Indices</hi> of the heart.</p>
                  <p>Many Hypocrites there are who for feare of cenſure, or deſire of eſteeme, keepe their tongues cleanly, and yet there is many a foule corner in their hearts: like thoſe Citizens who ſweepe and keepe their doores verie neare for feare of a checke from the Magiſtrate, and yet haue many a ſluttiſh corner in their houſes. When all is done, <hi>The Lord is the true beholder of the heart.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Homo cor ex verbis Deus verba ex corde penſat. Greg. Wiſd. <hi>1.6.</hi> Rom. <hi>1.20. 1.</hi> Sam. <hi>16.7.</hi> Pſal. <hi>139.2.</hi> Acts <hi>15.8.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Of him it is cleerly ſeene: He ſeeth not as man ſeeth; for man looketh on the outward appearance, but the Lord looketh on the heart. Hee vnderſtandeth our thoughts afarre off. Hee ſeeth in ſecret,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. Therefore <hi>Peter</hi> recordeth in the <hi>Acts,</hi> that it is <hi>God who knoweth the hearts:</hi> And God appropriateth that prerogatiue to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>I the Lord ſearch the heart.</hi> All things, and thoughts are naked and open in his eyes: The Fig-tree leaues could not keepe <hi>Adams</hi> nakedneſſe out of his ſight. The Fig-tree could not hide <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel</hi> from his priuie ſearch. Neither Men nor Angels but by eſpeciall reuelation from him can haue any hand in the ſearch of the heart,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.30.</note> 
                     <hi>for hee only knoweth the hearts of the children of men. The Heart is in the hand of the Lord.</hi> I turne my ſpeech to the conuerſion of the heart, which is another prerogatiue belonging to the Almightie hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27611:8"/>The heart it is, that is <hi>Primum viuens,</hi> the firſt part that is viuified and quickned, both in Nature and Grace. As when Subiects are vp in Rebellion, the Prince intending to ſubdue them, ſeizeth firſt on their ſtrongeſt hold: ſo God in reducing our rebell wills to his obedience, firſt layeth hold on the heart. Silly man is no otherwiſe the cauſe of his owne conuerſion, then <hi>Marcus Liuius</hi> was of the taking of <hi>Taren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> who (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> relateth) enuying <hi>Fabius</hi> for his recouering and reducing of it to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> obedience,<note place="margin">Plut. in vita Fab. Maximi.</note> in open Senate ſaid, That it was himſelfe and not <hi>Fabius</hi> that was the cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining the Citie: True anſwered <hi>Fabius,</hi> For hadſt not thou loſt it, I had neuer wonne it. <hi>Non potuiſti, ô homo, in te, niſi perdere te,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine; We haue gone aſtray like lost Sheepe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) It is the Lord that muſt <hi>ſeeke his Seruants.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.176.</note> It is our ſpirit that animates vs in nature, but Gods Spirit quickneth vs in Grace, and <hi>createth a cleane heart in vs.</hi> In Nature, the agilitie of our hands is to be attributed to our hearts. In Grace, the abilitie of our hearts to the hand of the Lord: His hand leadeth vs to ſauing health. Our hearts by ſinne were not only wounded, but altogether dead, ſtone-dead, lumpes of dead fleſh: Chriſt Ieſus that good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> came by, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Oyle and Wine, the Oyle of his mercie, and the red Wine that came from no other Vine, beſides his owne veines. Twas only the bloud of that Scape-goate who tooke our nature vpon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27611:8"/>
him that could mollifie our <hi>Adamantine</hi> hearts. We did no way preuent his abſolute worke of conuerſion by our owne wils preparation, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination. But as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of the Soule, <hi>That it was created together with the infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it, and infuſed into vs together with the creating of it:</hi> ſo muſt we of our will, that <hi>God in conuerting our hearts, maketh them to will their conuerſion, and in making our hearts to will their conuerſion, doth conuert them.</hi> And thus much of the Heart with reference to men in generall.</p>
                  <p>Now as all Clay is in the hand of the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet he is moſt carefull of that Clay which he reſerueth for veſſels which ſhall ſerue for the beſt vſes, and which hee will ſet at the higheſt rate: ſo <hi>God faſhioneth all hearts alike</hi> (as the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> noteth) &amp; yet he is moſt intentiue to the hearts of Kings. And good reaſon. The ſpirits &amp; hearts of priuate men, moue their priuate bodies; The ſpirits &amp; hearts of Princely and Publick perſons, moue multitudes, euen the whole bodie Politicke. Therefore God inſpireth the hearts of ſupreame Gouernours with heroicall gifts, and ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent graces, filleth them with fortitude and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie; and frameth and fitteth them for the managing of the weightieſt affaires. The hearts of priuate men are in the hands of the Lord, as the Wels of water, their motions are confined within their owne compaſſe: <hi>The heart of the King like the riuers of water</hi> (as yee may ſee in the words following the Text) from him there is to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27611:9"/>
be deriued the whole Weale publicke: <hi>The Spirit of God mooueth</hi> principally <hi>on thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As when the Riuer <hi>Nilus</hi> in his inundation ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſome Cubits higher then his vſuall limits, it is ſaid to bee a certaine preſage of a future Dearth and Famine in <hi>Aegypt:</hi> ſo when the Kings heart ſwelleth aboue the Lords hand, it will fill heauie on the whole Land.</p>
                  <p>And now from that which hath beene taught touching the Lords hand, both Kings and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects may learne to humble themſelues vnder Gods mightie hand, and to preſent them hearts vnto him with an <hi>Ecce Ancillam, Behold thine Hand-maide.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe Kings may take correction at Gods hand, who, as though God had no intereſt in their principall part, pay the vſe of it to their owne pleaſures; who liue rather like ſuch as thinke Gods heart to bee in their hand, then thoſe who conſider that theirs is in his; who direct not any Prayers vnto him, pray not vnto him for any directions, but making Idols of themſelues, cry <hi>Fiat voluntas nostra,</hi> let our wils be done. It is true indeed, that the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of Kings are exceeding great. They are in a great meaſure like vnto God himſelfe. For ſuch maieſtie he giueth them, that <hi>all people, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and languages tremble and feare before them; whom they will they ſlay, &amp; whom they will they keep
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27611:9"/>
aliue, whom they will they ſet vp, and whom they will they put downe, Dan.</hi> 5.19. Their hearts are vnſearchable, <hi>Prou.</hi> 25.3. Their power is in ſome ſort like vnto his:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.31.</note> 
                     <hi>Againſt him there is no riſing vp.</hi> And (like him) they are not bound to giue men an account of their actions; For as <hi>none can ſtay the Lords hand, and ſay vnto him what doeſt thou, Dan.</hi> 4. So, who ſhall ſay to the King what doſt thou.</p>
                  <p>Yet for all this, the ſame mouth that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth them <hi>Gods,</hi> telleth them that they ſhall <hi>dye like men:</hi> They may be as Gods to their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, yet muſt they bee ſubiect to God. As his hand hath aduanced them, ſo muſt they exalt him. This ſhall they doe when <hi>Maximus</hi> and <hi>Optimus</hi> goe hand in hand,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Virtus &amp; ſumma poteſtas</l>
                     <l>Cum cocant—</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>When in their Kingdomes they thinke of Gods Kingdome. Although <hi>Caput Imperij</hi> ſeeme to be the more glorious Title, yet <hi>Membrum Eccleſiae</hi> is the more gracious Name. <hi>Gratius nomen pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quam potestatis,</hi> ſayth <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apologet. cap. <hi>34</hi>
                     </note> And to ſpeake truly, Goodneſſe is the onely true Greatneſſe: They are great who are great in Gods fauour. So <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> were great: <hi>Iſidores</hi> Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie may ſerue to this purpoſe, <hi>Reges à rectè agendo,</hi> ſaith hee, as if <hi>Regere</hi> were nought elſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27611:10"/>
but <hi>rectè agere,</hi> with him agreeth <hi>Hugo Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> in his Comment, (if wee apply thoſe words to Kings in particular, which he vſeth in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) <hi>Cor Regale eſt, quod excuſsit à ſe iugum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitutis malae, nec alicui ſeruit, niſi Deo, cui ſeruire regnare eſt. Hee that ruleth ouer men muſt bee iuſt, ruling in the feare of God,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23 3. <hi>Rex eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> dum benè regis, quod niſi feceris, nomen Regis in te non conſtabit:</hi> ſo wrote <hi>Eleutherius</hi> to King <hi>Lucius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, the Lords hand in this Text may ſerue to checke thoſe Court-palmiſters, who thinke that they haue found the line of their prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their owne hands, ſaying in their hearts, <hi>Our hand is high, and the LORD hath not done all this, Deuteronomy</hi> 32.27. <hi>By the ſtrength of our hand we haue done it, and by our wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for wee are prudent, Eſay</hi> 10.13. O they ſhould thinke of an higher hand, and conſider that as they rule by Kings, ſo <hi>Kings raigne by God, Prou.</hi> 8. Therefore when they are exalted, they ſhould extoll Gods hand, and lift vp their owne, onely in prayſe to him: They ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that promotion commeth vnto them at the ſecond hand, For <hi>Promotion commeth neither from the Eaſt nor from the Weſt, nor from the South; But God is the Iudge, hee putteth downe one, and ſetteth vp another, Pſal.</hi> 75. Therefore that ſhould be their acknowledgement, and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was Kings <hi>Dauids,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.12. <hi>Both riches and honour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>come of thee, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27611:10"/>
thou raigneſt ouer all, and in thine hand is power and might, and in thine hand it is to make great,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now therefore our God wee thanke thee, and praiſe thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, let the ſame hand ſerue to beat downe thoſe preſumptious miſcreants, who durſt to lay violent hands on the Lords anointed ſeruants. It is fabled of the Bird Amphibia, that when the King of Fowles demanded tribute of her, ſhee tooke wing, and betooke her ſelfe to the Sea, and liued among the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hes, &amp;c. Birds of this feather are our Engliſh Fugitiues, the Popes Birds, who haue forſaken our Land, and betaken themſelues to the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> breaking aſunder the bonds of their Allegiance and Religion. Their adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Mother-Church ſaith vnto them concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſts pretended Vicar, that which Chriſts Virgin-Mother ſaid concerning Chriſt to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants at the marriage in <hi>Cana, Whatſoeuer he ſaith vnto you, doe it:</hi> And hee being (like the off ſpring of <hi>Herodias) before inſtructed by the</hi> curſed doctrine of that bloudie <hi>Mother,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.8.</note> breatheth out nothing but Murthers, biddeth them ayme at nothing ſo much, as at the heads of the Lords Anointed.<note place="margin">So was the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> King, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.5. And that blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <hi>Scythian</hi> of later times. <hi>Punientur iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio Dei. Lactant. Diu. Infi: lib</hi> 5. <hi>cap. vlt.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But wee are to learne hence a leſſon of Prayer and Supplication for Kings, and thoſe which are in authoritie; And of Patience and ſufferance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yoke of tyrannie: If our Kings tyrannize they are the ſcourge of God, as was <hi>Antiochus.</hi> They are in the Lords hand to puniſh vs, and wee muſt leaue and referre their puniſhment to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27611:11"/>
ſame hand: And certainely, <hi>his hand ſhall finde out all his enemies, Pſal.</hi> 21.8. When God openeth his hand, and layeth it graciouſly on thoſe who are our heads, then hee falleth to bleſſing of vs: when he ſhutteth it, and layeth it grieuouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our Heads, then hee falleth to buffetting of vs. Wherefore bee our Kings good? <hi>they are the Ministers of God for our good:</hi> Bee they euill? <hi>Indignationis aduerſus nos diuinae quaſi ministri ſunt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactant. diuin. Inſtit. lib, <hi>5.</hi> cap. vlt.</note> ſaith <hi>Lactantius.</hi> Good Kings are like fire to comfort and enlighten: Bad Kings are as fire to conſume and deuoure: It is not good medling with, or laying hands on either. What if <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzars heart bee lifted vp,</hi> muſt a ſentence of Depriuation bee giuen to deſpoile him of his throne?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.20 21.</note> No, Gods hand with the turne of an hand, muſt turne him a grazing, and <hi>make his Heart like the Beasts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.23.</note>Let <hi>Belſhazzar lift vp himſelfe againſt the Lord of Heauen;</hi> muſt a cenſure of Excommunication bee hung vp at his gate? No, the <hi>finger of the Lords hand muſt write againſt the wall of his Palace, that hand</hi> muſt <hi>number his time and finiſh it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.24.</note> 
                     <hi>weigh him in the ballance and finde him wanting, diuide his Kingdome and giue it to the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians. If the foule mouth of <hi>Herod</hi> breathe out from a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and cruell heart, threatnings againſt Gods Church: muſt a Chaſtell therefore ſtrike at his throat, or a <hi>Rauilliacke</hi> ſtab at his heart? No, the Lord muſt lay his hand vpon him: <hi>his Angels must ſmite him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:27611:11"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Horat.</note>Regum timendorum in proprios greges,</l>
                     <l>Reges in ipſos imperium eſt Dei.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord, as the Riuers of water.</hi> Wee muſt conſider that <hi>God withholdeth the waters and they drye vp, alſo he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them out and they ouerturne the Earth, Iob</hi> 12.15. See alſo, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Hee can cut off the ſpirit of Princes, Pſal.</hi> 76.12 Hee can change the hearts of Kings who are ſet to doe euill: Hee can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change Kings whom hee hath ſet as the hearts in the midſt of the Bodies politicke: Hee can alter and ſubuert the eſtates of Kingdomes though they bee ſet, and as it were ſetled in the very heart of the Earth, like that of the Iewes, <hi>Ezek. 5.5. Hee taketh away Kings; Hee ruleth ouer the Kingdomes of men, and giueth them to whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hee will. Magna Magnus diſponit Deus:</hi> So that wee muſt leaue thoſe things with all our hearts, to the diſpoſall of Gods Almightie hand. <hi>When the righteous are in authoritie the people reioyce</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, Prou.</hi> 29.2. <hi>When the wicked beare rule,</hi> what then, muſt the people rebell? No (as it there followeth) <hi>then the people mourne:</hi> They change their note and tune it to lachrymae: <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of waters runne downe their eyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe of thoſe</hi> Princes <hi>who keepe not Gods Law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bee our Kings then good or euill, God hath ſet them as <hi>the tree of good and euill in the midst of the Garden;</hi> It is not for man to touch them leaſt hee dye: <hi>Nemo potentes aggredi tutus poteſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> Engliſh it in the words of holy Scripture, <hi>Who can lay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27611:12"/>
hands vpon the Lords anointed and bee guiltleſſe,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. A thought againſt the ſacred head of Soueraigntie, is an attempt againſt thine owne: <hi>Scelus in autorem redit:</hi> like an arrow ſhot againſt heauen, it commeth downe with a vengeance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Shooters owne head. It is like that enue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed cup of the Monke of <hi>Swinſteed,</hi> which (as ſome write) deſtroyed himſelfe together with his Soueraigne: Or like that ſword wherewith <hi>Caſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſtrooke <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plut. in vit. Iulii Caeſaris.</note> which (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſtorieth) did afterward ſlay <hi>Caſsius</hi> himſelfe. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.15. The thoughts and the dreames of ſome haue beene treaſonable: But who would haue thought that their owne confeſſion ſhould make them plead guiltie? who would haue dream't that their fancie ſhould bee puniſht as a fact? <hi>Si nemo fuerit accuſator, ipſi narrabunt.</hi> The Lord hath bound euery heart and hand with ſuch a tye of inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience to their Kings, that <hi>who ſo prouoketh them to Anger, is ſaid to ſinne againſt his owne ſoule, Prou.</hi> 20.2. The Lord is ſo tender ouer them, that hee will not haue them touched; <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, Pſal.</hi> 105.15.</p>
                  <p>Hee telleth vs, that <hi>if the King bee curſed in our thought, or in our Bed chamber, a Bird of the Ayre ſhall carrie the voice, that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter, Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20.</p>
                  <p>When by <hi>Gowries</hi> Plot, our late Lord the King was brought euen to the Chambers of death, who would haue imagined that the tongue, ſcarce at libertie, ſhould haue diſcouered that the head was in danger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:27611:12"/>In the Powder-plot, when all things were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in ſecrecie: when thoſe bloud-ſuckers ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their cruell reſolutions with receit of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, therein mingling bloud with their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; who would haue thought that <hi>that which had wings ſhould haue told the matter;</hi> that a Quil, that a Letter, like that <hi>Anſer Capitolinus,</hi> ſhould haue bewrayed the capitall danger likely to fall vpon the whole Land? It was the <hi>hand of the Lord,</hi> that enlarged the <hi>heart of the King,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the intricate meaning of an obſcure Riddle. It was <hi>his hand</hi> that <hi>diſcouered deepe things out of darkeneſſe, and brought to light the ſhaddow of Death Iob</hi> 12.22. So the <hi>Cateſbeian</hi> Conſpiracie was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed much like the <hi>Catilinarian,</hi> of whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie <hi>Plutarch</hi> reporteth thus.<note place="margin">Plut. in vit. Ciceronis.</note> 
                     <hi>At night after ſupper, and not long before the Maſſacre ſhould haue beene committed,</hi> Craſſus <hi>his ſeruant brought him a packet of letters, deliuered him by a ſtranger vnknowne, was amongſt which one hauing no name ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, was directed to</hi> Craſſus, <hi>the effect of which was that there ſhould bee a great ſlaughter committed in</hi> Rome <hi>by Catiline, and therefore prayed him to forbeare the Citie:</hi> Craſſus <hi>therefore went to</hi> Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, <hi>partly for feare of the danger, and partly to cleare himſelfe from the ſuſpition of any league betweene him and the Conſpirators;</hi> Cicero <hi>conuented the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and cauſed the ſaid letters to bee read publickly and ſo thoſe letters bewrayed the Conſpiracie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let vs now change but a few names with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh <hi>Rome,</hi> and wee ſhall find but ſmall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27611:13"/>
in the reuealing of theſe two Romiſh and helliſh Conſpiracies: namely, if we put <hi>Cateſby</hi> for <hi>Catiline, Monteagle</hi> for <hi>Craſſus,</hi> our <hi>Cecil</hi> for her <hi>Cicero,</hi> &amp; our late Soueraigne for her whole Senat.</p>
                  <p>Thus the <hi>Lords</hi> mightie <hi>hand hath done for vs great things, and holy is his name. It hath ſcattered the proud in the imagination of their owne hearts, and holpen our Iſrael in remembrance of his mercie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To contract and conclude all, and therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, in a neerer application of this Text, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelues vnto thankes.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Let vs publiſh the name</hi> and the hand <hi>of our Lord: Aſcribe ye great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto our God:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.9.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lords portion is his people, and Iacobs</hi> off-ſpring <hi>the Lot of his Inheritance.</hi> As for his People; <hi>with his owne right hand hath hee gotten the victorie</hi> ouer the ſtrong holdes of their crooked and ſtubborne hearts. It was his onely <hi>hand</hi> that pierced that filme which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolueth their <hi>hearts,</hi> making it to ſend forth that cordiall water of compunction, the ſhedding whereof mortifieth Nature, and irrigateth the grace of their Conuerſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.10.12.</note>And as for <hi>Iacobs</hi> off-ſpring, <hi>the Lords hand brought him backe</hi> not long ſince, <hi>from a deſert Land: He led him about, he inſtructed him, hee kept him as the apple of his eye. The Lord alone did lead him and there was no ſtrange God with him;</hi> (that I may ſo apply thoſe paſſages in <hi>Moſes</hi> his Song, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.) The <hi>Lords hand</hi> fortified his Royall <hi>heart</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all danger both of ſoule and bodie, ſo that the Idolatrous Nation could neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne his perſon, nor obtayne their purpoſes.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27611:13"/>
Their looſe Religion did knit him faſter to his Lord and Sauiour: and their ſuperſtitious ſhewes and ſeruices did the more confirme his ſacred reſolution of perſiſting with ſinceritie of heart in the Orthodoxe and Apoſtolicall Faith. Yea, the ſame <hi>hand</hi> did in ſome ſort reuerſe the purpoſes of our Soueraigne himſelfe, to reſerue him for the accompliſhment of Gods owne diuine pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.1.</note> Hee who is the <hi>Roſe of Sharon and the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Valleyes</hi> brought backe our Soueraigne <hi>Roſe</hi> from that barren ſoyle, in whoſe Plot hee could neuer haue proſpered, the ground thereof being ſo deceitfull; And now hee hath bedded it with the Royall <hi>Lilly</hi> in his owne fruitfull Land. O let the Almightie <hi>Hand</hi> knit vp their hearts both together as one Poeſie in the bundle of life, making him alway a fragrant Roſe of a ſweet ſmelling ſauour before God; And her the <hi>turnd Lilly</hi> vnto the Lord; <hi>bearing vp both of them, that they may not daſh the foot</hi> of their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <hi>againſt the ſtone,</hi> and ſtumbling blocke of Idolatry, but rather, may daſh that in pieces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rocke Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>In the next place conſider wee how graciouſly the Royall Protector of the Soueraigne heart, hath enclined the royall heart of our gracious Soueraigne, to be the Protector and Auenger of his diſtreſſed Siſter and Nephewes in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> whoſe Land Strangers haue deuoured, and in whoſe low eſtate the heart of Religion hath long layen vpon bleeding. Finally, let <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:27611:14"/>
Tribe gratefully conſider, and remember how the Lord enlarged (the other day) the heart of our graciouſly enclined Soueraigne for the enlarging of <hi>Leuies</hi> portion, many of whoſe Tribe want the corporall bread, while they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the ſpirituall food. As ſoone as our Lord the King had notice from his loyall Subiects, that there was in many barren places of his Maieſties large Dominions, a Famine by ſo much greater then that in <hi>Samaria,</hi> (2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6.) by how much the Soule is better then the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. And that in thoſe places, it fared with his people as it did with thoſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> in the 25. Verſe of the forementioned Chapter; Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious Simonyaks obtruding to them by way of <hi>ſale, an Aſſes head</hi> to feed their hunger-ſtarued ſoules; yea an Head poſſeſſed with a dumbe ſpirit, whoſe jaw-bone euen while it wanteth motion may bee ſaid to ſlay as many Soules, as <hi>Samſon</hi> did Bodies with his <hi>Iaw-bone of an Aſſe, (Iudges</hi> 15.) <hi>heapes vpon heapes,</hi> as it is in the 16. Verſe of the Chapter. Hauing graciouſly laid to heart that this was the <hi>Kings Euill,</hi> and by him only to bee cured vnder God; and that therefore his Subiects did cry like her in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> [2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6.26.] <hi>Helpe our Lord, O King;</hi> He ſoone returned a more comfortable anſwer then ſhe receiued there; namely, <hi>that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled at that time ſhould take ſpeciall care, that for the better propagating of the Goſpell in prouiding able Pastors, prouiſion ſhould bee made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27611:14"/>
that aſwell the owners of Parſonages Impropriate, as the Inhabitants of Pariſhes vntaught, ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low competent maintenance for ſufficient Miniſters, in thoſe Churches, whoſe Cures did neerely concerne themſelues in particular.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus the Lord hath highly enriched our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne with the bleſſings of <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſo that <hi>hee is wiſe in his youth, and as a Floud filled with vnderſtanding: His Name is gone farre,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ecclus</hi> 47.14, 16.</note> 
                     <hi>and for the peace</hi> and proſperitie which he wiſheth vnto <hi>Sion,</hi> he is highly <hi>beloued</hi> and renowned.</p>
                  <p>And as for the Iles vnder him, the Lord hath bleſſed them with the bleſſings of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the laſt Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 66. <hi>cap. verſ.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee hath extended peace like a Riuer, our hearts reioyce, and our bones flouriſh like an hearbe, and the hand of the Lord is knowne towards vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the ſame Almightie hand of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing God who hath placed and planted our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne as the Heart in the bodie of this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angled Iland, reſerue euer to it ſelfe only, that little Triangle of his heart, <hi>giue him an heart to loue and dread the Lord, and diligently to liue and rule according to his Commandements;</hi> that ſo, when hee ſhall haue <hi>finiſhed his courſe, kept the Faith, and giuen vp the Account of his high Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> hee may heare that comfortable and heart-reioycing voyce pronounced vnto him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 25.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note> 
                     <hi>Well done thou good and faithfull ſeruant, thou haſt beene faithfull ouer a few things; I will make thee ruler ouer many things: Enter thou into the Ioy of thy Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:15"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:15"/>
                  <p>A BRIEFE MEDITATION VPON THE FIF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEENTH VERSE OF the twenty fourth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſecond Booke of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deliuered at a vveekly Lecture in <hi>Deuon:</hi> Anno <hi>1625.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. P.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>THOV SHALT LABOR FOR PEACE PLEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE</p>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby.</hi> 1626.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:16"/>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:27611:16"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>2. SAM. 24.15.</bibl>
                        <p>So the Lord ſent a Pestilence vpon <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the morning euen vnto the time appointed, and there dyed of the people, euen from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> ſeuenty thouſand men.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>EE ſee euen at the firſt ſight that this Text affoordeth fit matter for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp of our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations in theſe times: It maketh report of a great Peſtilence ſpreading it ſelfe in <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the time, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the ſinne, of King <hi>Dauid. Dauids</hi> heart is lifted vp in the number of his people; The Lord lifteth vp his hand to cut it off. He pricketh that ſwelling bladder of vaine and carnall confidence, with a ſharpe and grieuous ſickneſſe.</p>
                  <p>I note in the Text theſe ſeuerall particulars,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:27611:17"/>Firſt, The Author or Inflicter of this morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; <hi>The Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, The Nature of it; It was <hi>a Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The time in which it raigned; <hi>From the morning euen to the time appointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, The Place to which it was confined; <hi>From Dan to Beerſheba.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiftly, The Number of people which it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; <hi>Seuentie thouſand men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, The Author is <hi>Iehoua The Lord,</hi> ſet out by that great Name of his, deriued from an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> word ſignifying <hi>Being,</hi> to ſhew and make knowne his independencie from any other, hee being an eternall <hi>Being</hi> of himſelfe. <hi>I am that I am, Exod.</hi> 3.14. and alſo to manifeſt that hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth being to all the creatures; whence ſome haue well obſerued that the name of <hi>Iehoua</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> was not vſed before the whole worke of the Creation was finiſhed, but is firſt mentioned in the ſecond Chapter and fourth Verſe of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</hi> And laſtly to giue vs to vnderſtand, that God giueth being and accompliſhment to all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, he cauſeth them to bee brought to paſſe, and become (as it were) things in <hi>Eſſe,</hi> in <hi>Being.</hi> Therefore God telleth <hi>Moſes</hi> in the ſixt Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> Verſe the third. That <hi>he was not knowne vnto Abraham, Iſaak and Iacob by his name Iehouah,</hi> becauſe though they beleeued that he would, yet they liued not to ſee that he did effectually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27611:17"/>
that which hee had graciouſly promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in deliuering their ſeed from the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> ſeruitude, and inueſting them with the poſſeſſion of the Land of promiſe. So then, the Inflicter of this great and terrible Peſtilence was <hi>Iehouah</hi> the Lord, a great God and a terrible, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtileth him; that vncauſed Being, the cauſe of all <hi>Being,</hi> who keepeth his word, and that ſpecially in the execution of his wrath vpon ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The Nature of the puniſhment by him inflicted was peſtilentiall, <hi>The Lord ſent a Pestilence, &amp;c.</hi> The ſickneſſe as wee call it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>viz.</hi> a moſt grieuous, deadly, violent and infectious diſeaſe, ſeizing on the ſpirits, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſending to the graue: A moſt vncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſickneſſe, in as much as when God viſiteth vs with it, all refraine from viſiting vs. <hi>Our Louers and friends ſtand aloofe from this ſore, and our Kinſmen ſtand afarre off,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in another, and more generall ſenſe, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 38.11.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, As for the time in which the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence raigned. Some ſay it was from morning to mid-day, ſome for the whole three dayes threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, A third ſort for halfe the ſpace: The Text ſaith it was <hi>euen to the time appointed:</hi> And if wee ſhall thinke that the triduall terme was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged vpon <hi>Dauids</hi> humiliation &amp; repentance; or at leaſt that the Plague ceaſed before the third day ended; the Lord being ſaid in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27611:18"/>
to <hi>repent of the euill,</hi> forbearing in his anger to puniſh, and forbidding his Angell to proceed any further, the phraſe of Scripture will bee our warrant, in which Gods temporall puniſhments are not euer decreed irreuocably, but determined conditionally, and if men will not repent, hee will proceed to accompliſhment: yet will it not therefore follow that Gods will dependeth vpon mans, for it is knowne to him from eternitie, who they are that ſhall turne to him by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and he is the orderer of their wayes, and the ouer-ruler of their wils, and their repentance is meerly of his grace, and from his gift.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, The place to which the Peſtilence was confined, was <hi>from Dan to Beerſheba. Dan</hi> is heere taken locally for a Citie bounding <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as elſewhere perſonally for a Sonne borne vnto <hi>Iacob:</hi> Twas the vtmoſt confine of <hi>Iſrael</hi> on the North ſide; as <hi>Beerſheba</hi> a Citie of <hi>Iudah</hi> was on the South, towards the <hi>Philiſtines:</hi> So <hi>from Dan to Beerſheba,</hi> is in effect throughout all <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Twere the like phraſe of ſpeech, if wee of theſe parts ſhould ſay of ſome generall Plague diſperſed in all the Iland of Great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> that it raigned from the Start-point on our Southerne Seas, vnto <hi>Straithy-head</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which is the fartheſt point ſtretching it ſelfe into the North Seas.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, The number that dyed were <hi>ſeuentie thouſand men.</hi> A great Catalogue for ſo ſmall a continuance, or in ſo ſmall a compaſſe: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27611:18"/>
that if the mortalitie ſhould haue held the ſame courſe which it beganne, but a moneth or two, it is likely (by conferring the number which <hi>Ioab</hi> tooke of the people, with the number which God tooke away by the Peſtilence) that in all <hi>Iſrael</hi> there would not haue beene a man or two left. I grant that it is apparant, that <hi>Ioab</hi> brought not an exact number of all the people, but withall I ſay, it is moſt probable, that all the people who fell by the Peſtilence are not heere numbred, but chiefly (if not only) thoſe whom God ſubtracted, and tooke away from the former computation of thoſe men of warre in whom <hi>Dauid</hi> gloried. So the Lord puniſhed <hi>Dauid</hi> in the thing wherein he offended God. <hi>Dauid</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried of the number of his people in his pride, and God diminiſhed them with his Plague.</p>
                  <p>Thus haue I ouer-runne the particulars to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to my obſeruations. I finde many a notable Emphaſis in this Text. Death is not ſo ſtrange, and yet there is notice to be taken of it: but for men to die of ſo ſtrange a death as of the peſtilence, and for ſo many to dye of the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and that in ſo ſmall a compaſſe of time, and within <hi>Iſraels</hi> Confines, this is that which ſhould force vs to take a more ſpeciall notice of the heauie hand of God.</p>
                  <p>The Obſeruation which I firſt draw out of this Text, is this:</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>The pestilence is Gods ſpeciall Rod, whereby he ſcourgeth the ſinne, and puniſheth the pride of the most potent and populous Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:27611:19"/>God had greatly multiplyed his great mercies vpon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in great mercie had greatly multiplyed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> made it a great and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Nation, of ſmall beginnings; and now for <hi>Dauids</hi> ſinne of numbring, and for the number of their ſinnes, he beginneth greatly to diminiſh them. <hi>The Lord ſent a Pestilence.</hi> The Peſtilence is his great ſcourge for ſinne. <hi>When you are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in your Cities, I will ſend a Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence among you</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>viz. for your breach of my couenant, Leuiticus</hi> 26.25. Indeed euery ſickneſſe may be ſaid to bee Gods ſcourge, but the Plague, that is <hi>ſpecialis plaga,</hi> Gods ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and proper ſtripe, the ſignes that it makes are Gods ſpeciall markes, and therefore the Word of the Lord calleth it the Sword of the Lord, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.12. As <hi>Iehouah</hi> the name by which God is heere ſtiled is peculiar to him: ſo the ſpreading of the peſtilence, which hee here ſendeth is from him alone.</p>
                  <p>Wee may rayſe other ſickneſſes to caſt downe our ſelues by our owne ſurfets and diſtempers, this ſeemeth to bee meerly of his ſending, and he only to haue a finger heerein. So <hi>Dauid</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged when he choſe to <hi>fall into the hands of God,</hi> by the falling of his people by a Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, in the Verſe before the Text.</p>
                  <p>And now for vſe to vs; Beloued, <hi>Iſraels</hi> cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in the time of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> is <hi>Englands</hi> caſe in the time of King <hi>Charles,</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:27611:19"/>
                     <q>
                        <l>—Facta est narratio de te,</l>
                        <l>Anglia, mutato nomine, cum numero.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In changing the names of the countrie and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, together with the number of houres in which this Plague laſted, and of the people whom it conſumed while it continued, heere is our caſe, and wee haue an Engliſh hiſtorie.</p>
                  <p>If the Peſtilence then bee Gods ſcourge for ſin, let vs ſee what wee haue to doe to appeaſe him. Once wee can neuer goe from his puniſhments, as wee haue ſtrayed from his Precepts: hee can follow vs from London to the Mount, and from the Lands end to the middeſt of the Ocean: <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can wee goe from his preſence?</hi> there is no way for vs to flye from him, but by flying vnto him, and betaking our ſelues from the face of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to the footſtoole of his mercie: To amend our wayes, that is the onely way for vs to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe his wrath, and to end his plagues. For when wee are once duly humbled for our ſinnes, God hath attained his end and ayme in puniſhing vs, and then he will ſtay his hand. Whence elſe doth God complaine by <hi>Amos, That hee ſent the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence among the Iſraelites after the manner of Egypt</hi> (as now hee hath ſent the Peſtilence among the Engliſh after the manner of <hi>Iſrael) and yet they returned not vnto him, Am.</hi> 4.10. Wherefore doth he thus teſtifie and conteſt againſt them by <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai,</hi> that <hi>hee ſmote them and yet they turned not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, Hag.</hi> 2.17. True is the Sonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> his acknowledgement, <hi>Thou chastneſt and warneſt vs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27611:20"/>
that leauing our wickedneſſe, wee may beleeue on thee O Lord, Wiſd.</hi> 1.2. Well ſpeaketh <hi>Lactantius</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the purpoſe, <hi>Deus morum emendatione placatur, &amp; qui peccare deſinit iram Dei mortalem facit: To ceaſe from ſinne, is to make Gods anger ceaſe from vs; and to amend our wayes is the only way to auoide his plagues.</hi> Let vs then repent of the euill which wee haue wrought againſt God, that he may repent of the euill which he hath brought amongſt vs. Let vs repent, and not proceed in our ſinnes; that he may repent, and not proceed with his plagues: plagues, which though in our owne particulars wee feele not yet; yet wee muſt needes feare, and ſhould duly compaſſionate in others. For <hi>is the head ſicke, and doe not the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our members ſuffer with it;</hi> Or, if the head Citie continue ſicke, is it like to fare well with vs? May not we ſee our owne face in that London glaſſe? Certaine it is, that our raigning ſinnes haue made way for this raigning ſickneſſe. Our inward cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions beare a part in the cauſe of this conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Our ſinnes made a ſeparation betweene God and vs, ere euer he by this ſickneſſe hath made vs ſeparate one from another. Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider, and that with great ſorrow and humiliation, the great ſinnes wherewith wee haue prouoked him, equalling I am ſure, if not exceeding thoſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The chiefe ſinnes wherewith <hi>Iſrael</hi> prouoked God, were,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Their Intemperancie and Luxurie in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27611:20"/>
of thoſe outward bleſſings wherewith they abounded.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Their Inſolencie and ſecuritie by reaſon of the many victories which they had atchieued.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Their Ingratitude, not rendring due thanks for the benefits which they had receiued.</p>
                  <p>Theſe three were the <hi>Capitall</hi> ſinnes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in which <hi>Dauid</hi> as <hi>Head</hi> bare a principall part, and for which hee was put to ſo hard a choice, that he preferred the three dayes plague as the eaſieſt puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>God hath no way beene wanting to this our Iland in <hi>Iſraels</hi> bleſſings: She hath no way beene behind <hi>Iſrael</hi> in thoſe ſinnes. Hee hath bleſſed our Kingdome aboue neighbour Nations, with his protection and deliuerances, with peace and plentie, with a potent people, and aboue all, with the powerfull preaching of his glorious Goſpell. He hath exalted our times aboue former ages, by giuing and preſeruing vnto vs Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for pietie, wiſdome, and moderation, vnpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelled in our, or in other humane Chronicles: But how haue wee failed in bleſſing him, in magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and exalting his name?</p>
                  <p>Let our <hi>fulneſſe of bread,</hi> and vaine pleaſing of our ſelues in ſuch infinite varietie and exquiſite delicacie of feeding; our fulneſſe of pride, and vaine glorying in the ſtrength of our Land For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in remembrance of our nauall victories; Our vnthankfulneſſe to God for the free paſſage of his Goſpell, in deſpite of all plots and proiects
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27611:21"/>
to the contrarie, and for his manifold and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable deliuerances of Prince and People from tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous inuaſions and ſubtile circumuentions at home and abroad, our proneneſſe to depart from the Lord, and to <hi>goe a whoring after ſtrange Gods,</hi> as ſoone as our moſt religious Prince, and now gracious Soueraigne, was departed out of our Land into a ſtrange Nation; Our returning ſuch cold thankes for his ſo bleſſed returne into his owne inheritance. Our generall diſcontent; our eying of Egypt, and wiſhing this our <hi>Iſrael</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with, and enthralled vnto a nation in ſome conceits rich and mightie, but in all reſpects baſe and miſerable; Let theſe things, theſe ſinnes, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie againſt vs, and let this our ingratitude humble and caſt vs downe in a reuengefull iudging of our ſelues, as it hath called and pulled downe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and vengeance on vs.</p>
                  <p>O the ingratitude of a ſinfull nation! how greatly is it increaſed? Is it poſſible that we ſhould not daily conſider and celebrate Gods great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in hindering the intended Powder-plot, that cruell and confuſed Parliamentarie maſſacre, in which Babylons children ſet on worke by <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, had built the Tower of <hi>Babel</hi> againe with morter tempered with the publicke bloud, had not God <hi>confounded</hi> them in their owne <hi>language,</hi> and diſcouered them by their owne priuate Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And yet woe is vs, we ſuffer this to ſlip from vs. Yea all thoſe dagges, daggers, and dangers, thoſe piſtols, poynadoes, and poyſons, fitted,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27611:21"/>
whetted, and prepared, by Pope, Papiſts, and the Spaniſh faction, for the breaſts of our Royall and Religious Soueraignes, are now as it were caſed, and ſheathed, and bound vp in vtter obliuion and vnthankefulneſſe. And is it not iuſt with God to vnſheathe his ſword, and reſcue his bleſſings from vs, and reuenge our vnthankefulneſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs?</p>
                  <p>I cannot amplifie my ſpeech as this land hath multiplied her ſinne and ingratitude, yet I will deſire you to examin your ſelues with me a while in ſome few points, wherein I will inſtance, and whereon I deſire to inſiſt, (as the time ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) to the confuſion of our owne faces, and the clearing of Gods proceedings with vs, and our Land.</p>
                  <p>Haue not we euery day put off our repentance, and conſequently increaſed our ſinnes; and doe wee wonder why God day by day cutteth off ſuch rebels, and more and more increaſeth and ſpreadeth abroad the peſtilence?</p>
                  <p>Haue not we ſleighted or ſlandered Gods pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters, who haue denounced his iudgments againſt our ſinnes? And what maruaile if the plagues which they threatned againſt vs, be now entred amongſt vs?</p>
                  <p>Are there not amongſt vs many peſtilent ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of all goodneſſe and religion, who ſit euen in <hi>cathedra peſtilentiae,</hi> (there the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> placeth them) ſuch as terme holineſſe, without which no man can ſee God, peſtilent peruerſeneſſe, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27611:22"/>
peeuiſh preciſeneſſe; ſuch as tearme the Lords holy Embaſſadors (as <hi>Tertullus</hi> did <hi>Paul</hi>) peſtilence it ſelfe (ſo ſoundeth the Originall,) &amp; thoſe Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers who peſter their ſweet ſinnes, peſtilent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that is a common name with them; They make them the worſt of men, and the ſcumme of the Earth: And what maruaile if the peſtilence the fierceſt of all ſickneſſes, and the ſcourge of the earth be come among vs?</p>
                  <p>Doth not the Extortioner take intereſt, and the Oppreſſor vſe violence? doe they not eat like a canker into the eſtates of the poore, going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and ſeeking how and whom they may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach and deceiue? And doe we wonder why the peſtilence breaketh in vpon vs like a mightie tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſweepeth away our people, and taketh away our increaſe, <hi>going about like a roaring Lyon ſeeking whom it may deuoure?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Haue not many of vs vncharitably and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly wiſhed that the plague of God would light on our Brethren? And now, how iuſtly hath it euen ouertaken vs: So long haue oathes, curſes and execrations, ſuch as <hi>a vengeance take thee, and, a plague on thee, and, God confound thee,</hi> come out from vs like arrowes ſhot againſt heauen, till now they are readie to returne and fall downe with a vengeance on our owne heads. We haue called for them; and now they are comming. We haue tainted the ayre with them, and now the ayre is readie to enter and infect vs.</p>
                  <p>Haue not ſome of vs heartily wiſhed for our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27611:22"/>
Brethrens deaths that wee might compaſſe our deſignes, and grow great in the World; And now, how deſeruedly may their death in theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious times, be the bane of our whole Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Is there not the hiding (if not the plotting, as well as the packing vp) of Murthers among vs, (and all perhaps for the purſing of a piece of mony) And what maruell if our bloud bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and our Land vnpeopled, when that bloud is concealed which cryeth for vengeance, and leaueth a Land vnpurged.</p>
                  <p>Haue not the creatures been peruerted by vs in the intemperate and lawleſſe vſe of them: and what maruell if wee are now readie to bee infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by them, in their lawfull and moderate vſe? Our ſwelling humour of Pride and Gluttonie, in exceſſe of fare and apparell, ſwilling and ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering in the moſt riotous manner, hath made way for the ſwelling tumour of the peſtilence ſpreading and raging, abroad in our Land. The cloathes which ſhould haue couered our ſhame, and haue ſo ſhamefully diſcouered our pride; in ſteed of keeping vs well and warme, are now rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to conuay contagion into vs.</p>
                  <p>We haue ſhut our doores againſt the poore, <hi>the poore hath beene ſeparated from his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> and now we are in danger of hauing our doores ſhut vp, and our ſelues ſeparated one from another.</p>
                  <p>We haue infeſted others with our particular examples of diuers pernicious deeds; And now others are ready to infect vs with peſtilent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27611:23"/>
Our humour of corrupting others, hath at length brought the corruption of the humours on our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>Wee haue not feared the contagion of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners who haue beene notoriouſly incorrigible and ſcandalous; and now we can hardly eſcape thoſe whom wee iuſtly ſuſpect to be infectious.</p>
                  <p>In our priuate familiaritie wee haue not ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the precious from the vile, wee haue aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured vpon intimate acquaintance with the moſt peſtilent perſons, and peruerſeſt Sinners: and now thoſe who haue the very ſore of the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence running vpon them, are readie to ruſh in among vs.</p>
                  <p>In our priuate Families we haue had medly Liueries, garments of <hi>Linſey-wolſey,</hi> a mixture of bad ſeruants with ſome few good ones: Some we haue had of both ſorts, to bring our deſſignes to paſſe on both ſides; corrupt men, that our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ends might bee compaſſed; and religious men, that ſo they might bee coloured or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced. Wicked <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> there are among vs, who thinke they may ſinne with liberty, and purloyne for their commoditie, vnder a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that none can eſpie them, as long as Chriſts followers keepe their company. And now the ſicke are mingled with the ſound, and the one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered by the other.</p>
                  <p>Our eares haue itched after Nouelties and ſtrange opinions, and now behold a new and a ſtrange contagion is come among vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:27611:23"/>Many of vs haue affected Sects, Schiſme, and Separation, and now the ſickneſſe hath made a ſore rent, and a grieuous ſeparation amongſt vs. It hath been heard among vs that children might not bee baptized, and admitted into the Church without danger of ſinne: And now it may bee feared that they will not bee brought into the Congregation without danger of ſickneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Platoes</hi> communitie hath beene held by ſome particular Libertines, and now it may be feared that one common plague is let looſe to lay hold generally vpon all places.</p>
                  <p>To draw towards a concluſion; So ill haue wee couenanted with our ſenſes for the Lords ſeruice, that now all of them ſtriue to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to our ſelues, and are forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a grieuous ſubiection to the generall contagion that raigneth ouer the Land. The Smell hath beene taken with effeminate, if not Whoriſh perfumes; The Eare hath beene tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with vaine, if not villanous ſpeeches; The Taſte hath beene ouer-taken with Luxurie; The Touch tainted with Laſciuiouſneſſe; The Eye hath beene rolled with wandring Luſts, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſet vpon lewdneſſe. So ſlenderly haue we guarded theſe Cinque-ports of our Domeſticall Senſes, that now they are readie to let in, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enemie, in open ayre, to ouerthrow the whole eſtate of our bodies; as our Cinque-ports on the Sea-coaſt, if they be not watched, may proue dangerous in-lets, for our foes to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27611:24"/>
enter by, and endanger the bodie of our State. Thus <hi>the Lord is iuſt, but wee haue done wickedly.</hi> Now once more, what is the remedie whereby wee may auoid, or induce him to auert his plagues?</p>
                  <p>To keepe our Bodies from the peſtilentiall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the plague, we obſerue three ſpeciall directions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, To haſten from places infected.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, To remoue into a pure aire.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, To haue the preſcripts of the beſt Preſeruatiues and Medicines.</p>
                  <p>Wee muſt take a like courſe for our ſoules, againſt that plague of ſinne;</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Goe out from the occaſions of ſinne, as <hi>Peter</hi> did from the High Prieſts Hall.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Goe into a pure aire; get vs a pure heart and a conſcience purged, to which wee may retire in all danger; a heart and a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence clenſed by the wind of the Spirit, cooling our concupiſcence, and aſſwaging our boyling corruptions, and inſpiring vs with good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Get vs a <hi>Peter</hi>-teare, a bitter wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, proceeding from a true faith in Chriſt, and a due contrition for ſinne; bewayling our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the cauſes of theſe contagions. That, that is the onely diſtilled water, which fortifieth vs againſt all Gods plagues. For if his ſcourge once induce vs to penitence, it muſt (conſidering our deſeruing) needs endue vs with patience, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27611:24"/>
then whatſoeuer befalleth vs, <hi>It ſhall goe well with vs, and happie ſhall we be.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I proceed to that which followeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord ſent a Peſtilence vpon Iſrael from the morning to the time appointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>From the morning to the time appointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence may we gather, that</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>The ſpreading and ſpeeding of peſtilent contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is both appointed, and limited by God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He ſendeth them, and he reſtrayneth them. They ſhall rage no longer then the appointed time: they ſhall rid no more but Gods appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet number. Heere the people dye of the plague, and the King eſcapeth; In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Kings</hi> the twentieth Chapter, the King is ſicke of the plague, and the people free: here, though the popular plague were threatned for three dayes ſpace, yet it ceaſed before the terme was fully expired, and there, though King <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> were told from God that hee ſhould die, yet hee humbling himſelfe, was rayſed as it were from his death-bed, recouered from his diſeaſe, and the Lord added to his dayes.</p>
                  <p>We reade in Hiſtories of diuers great &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall plagues, ſome raigning ouer all the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> as that in the yeere 1348. vnder <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Third, ſome raging ouer all the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Empire, as that in the yeere 252. vnder <hi>Vibius Gallus</hi> that peſtilent perſecutor of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith. Both which plagues, and ſpecially the latter, in their ſeuerall times (as Hiſtorians
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27611:25"/>
relate) creeping throughout all the Regions of the Earth, laſted very long, and waſted many Millions of people: Inſomuch that <hi>Cyprian</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an occaſion by reaſon of the greater of thoſe two generall plagues, to write his Booke <hi>De Mortalitate,</hi> ſaith, towards the end of that Tract, <hi>Corruit iam mundus malorum infestantium turbinibus obſeſſus, That the World was euen waſted and went to wracke with the boyſterous ſtormes of maladies and moleſtations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now who ſpreadeth theſe plagues, who bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the earth in this ſickneſſe, but hee who ſpreadeth the Heauens as a Curtaine? <hi>Hee</hi> who <hi>with-holdeth the waters and they dry vp,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.15.</note> 
                     <hi>and alſo ſendeth them out, and they ouerturne the earth:</hi> He reſtraineth the peſtilence, and the ſore dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vp, hee ſendeth it forth, and it ouerunneth the Earth; <hi>he maketh deſolations in the Earth, Pſal.</hi> 46.8. Againe, <hi>he maketh</hi> the plague, as he doth the plague of <hi>warre,</hi> in the Verſe there following, <hi>to ceaſe vnto the end of the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Many there are, who haue ſtretched their wits to diſcourſe how the Lord ſhould cauſe the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence to ſpread and diſperſe it ſelfe abroad. Diuers men referre it to diuers meanes: ſome affirming that all thoſe who fall by the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, are felled by the immediate ſtroke of Gods puniſhing Angell. Others conceiuing, that the euill one, who diſtilleth into the malicious minds of many who are infectious a deſire to infect others, as hee doth into the mindes of the ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, a delight to ſeduce others, that hee I ſay,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27611:25"/>
conueyeth contagious infection from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, deriuing it from place to place, from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to perſon, by apparell, ayre and all thoſe arts which hee is permitted to vſe againſt a people whom God purpoſeth to viſit.</p>
                  <p>Sure I am, here is the lamentable effect of the peſtilence ſet downe in this Chapter, on which the preſent calamitie of our owne country ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſo large a Comment: here is laid downe the prime Author that layeth it on, the maine cauſe that leades him on, and the meanes inducing him to leaue off. The meanes of diſperſing the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence muſt be left to him alſo; they are in his hands who can vſe what meanes hee will to accompliſh his iuſt purpoſes, and to puniſh a rebellious nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For vſe of the point. In that God ſpreadeth the peſtilence, wee ſee how wide they are of the truth, who impute it rather to the fate of deſtiny, or the influence of malignant ſtarres, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of much people, or the cloſeneſſe of place, or the corruption of the ayre, or the inundation of waters, or the repletion of humors, then to the hand of God, who diſpoſeth of all theſe at his pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>Againe we may learne that they doe but ſpred a net for their owne feet, who thinke or ſeeke to flye from the ſpreading peſtilence, without flying vnto God. Alas, it is not the auoiding of places infected, nor the correcting of ayres cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, nor the taking of receits preſcribed, not the putting off of cloathes ſuſpected, that can
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27611:26"/>
ſecure thee from Gods plagues. The arrow of Gods anger can paſſe ſwiftly through the Ayre, and enter ſecretly into thy boſome, as that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row did into the King of <hi>Iſraels</hi> bodie, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the change of place or attire.<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.30, 34.</note> It is not the change of Ayre or rayment, but the change of the heart by repentance that can ſtand thee in ſtead. Though thou preſently ſhift thy ſelfe, ſhirt and all, yet there is no ſhifting from God; hee will finde thee out. Indeed the outward meanes of preſeruation are to bee ſought and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but not relyed on. When Gods arrowes flye abroad, we muſt primarily arme our ſelues with prayer and flye vnto God, as <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> did, when his enemies came againſt him. <hi>If euill come vpon vs</hi> (ſaith he to the Lord) <hi>as the ſword, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.9.</note> &amp;c. <hi>And wee ſtand in thy preſence and cry vnto thee, thou wilt heare and helpe:</hi> He knew that his Progenitor and Predeceſſor <hi>Aſa</hi> had felt the ſmart of the contrarie practice, who did not ſo much pray vnto God, as deſire the Phyſicians to practice with him,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12.</note> and therefore the Lord made their helpes vnprofitable.</p>
                  <p>In the next place here might bee drawne an vſe of comfort for Gods Children, in that the ſword is in the hand of their mercifull father, <hi>who will not euer be angrie,</hi> but correct them in meaſure, and compaſſe them with his mercie: But there is another vſe to bee made, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other doctrine likewiſe to be raiſed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not inſiſt on it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:27611:26"/>The laſt vſe then, (that wee may more neerly apply a point that ſo neerely concerneth vs) ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for direction vnto vs all. Doth the Lord ſpread the peſtilence among vs, and ſend it out like a running armie, waſting whereſoeuer it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal</hi> 91.6.</note>
                     <hi>walking in the darkneſſe and waſting at noone day: like a raging</hi> and deuouring <hi>raine, leauing no food:</hi> like an vniuerſall blaſt deſtroying all fruits? Doth hee make his dreadfull forces poſt hither and thither, amidſt our preparations for warre, as hee did among <hi>Dauids</hi> warlike people? What ſhould we then doe but as weaker countryes are accuſtomed, vpon the approch of dreadfull Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; ſubmit our ſelues, ſend our Agents, and ſue for peace. Conſider we, what thoſe of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> did in the dayes of <hi>Herod, Act.</hi> 12. towards the end of that Chapter: When they vnderſtood that <hi>Herod</hi> did beare an hoſtile minde towards them, <hi>they ſent their Ambaſſadors with one accord to deſire peace.</hi> But as for vs, <hi>mittamus legatos do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris noſtri lachrymas,</hi> let vs with ioynt conſent ſend forth plentifull teares, as the onely preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent oratorie of a pierced and wounded heart. For as great flouds hinder the preparations of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: ſo the teares of humiliation ſtay Gods pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing hand. With teares let vs ioyne prayers, pouring out our ſoules like water before the Lord. When the Lord bid <hi>Hezekiah</hi> prouide for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death, <hi>he prayed and wept ſore:</hi> hereupon the Lord heareth his prayers, ſeeth his teares healeth his ſore, and lengtheneth his dayes. And in this
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27611:27"/>
Chapter, God hauing denounced a three dayes peſtilence, doth yet vpon <hi>Dauids</hi> humble petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhorten the time, and in the time appointed ceaſe the plague which hee threatned: They of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> made <hi>Blastus the Kings Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> their friend; but as for vs, <hi>non Blaſtum, ſed Chriſtum Interceſſorem habeamus;</hi> Let vs not ſue or ſeeke to thoſe glorious Seruants, and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaines of the Almightie, who ſtand euer in his preſence, not to <hi>Seraphins</hi> or <hi>Cherubins,</hi> not to <hi>Saints</hi> or <hi>Angels;</hi> But as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> tooke vp the Sonne of King <hi>Admet</hi> into his armes,<note place="margin">Plut. in vit. Themiſtoc.</note> that by him hee might appeaſe the angrie father: ſo let vs take vp Chriſt the Sonne of God by the hand of faith, and ſet his merits betweene vs and his fathers wrath, that hee may dull the point of his puniſhing ſword, in the wounds of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Sonne. O let vs make him our friend, that hee may make our peace with God; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, teares, and prayers, they are all in vaine, no better then the howling of dogs or the lowing of Oxen. Let vs goe out of all confidence in our Selues, in our Worthies, in our Allyes, in our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in our Nauies; and ſtripping our ſelues na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, caſt our ſelues ouer-board into the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Sea of his mercie, as our onely ſafeguard and ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, they of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> in the height of blaſphemous flatterie, hearing the <hi>Herodian</hi> oration, ſaid it was <hi>the voice of God and not of Man:</hi> But let vs in the depth of a contrite peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27611:27"/>
feeling the hand of God, ſay and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that it is the ſtroke of God and not of man; and that it is in vaine to looke for any helpe but from him. <hi>Vna manus nobis vulnus opem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> feret.</hi> The hand that caſts vs downe, can onely raiſe vs vp. It is God that dealeth with vs of <hi>England</hi> now, as of old he did with <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.14.</note> 
                     <hi>taking away when none can reſcue;</hi> If wee ſhall crye vnto him, <hi>how long Lord;</hi> It may bee anſwered, (as it followeth in the next verſe of the ſame Chapter) <hi>till wee acknowledge our offence, and ſeeke his face:</hi> O let our hearts anſwer in the Pſalmiſts Eccho, <hi>Thy face O Lord will wee ſeeke.</hi> So it followeth againe in the ſame verſe, <hi>In their affliction they will ſeeke mee early;</hi> they are the laſt words of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Then according to that ioynt-motion for a generall humiliation, in the beginning of the ſixt and next Chapter; <hi>Come let vs returne vnto the Lord, for he hath torne and hee will heale vs, hee hath ſmitten and hee will bind vs vp:</hi> This doing, as it there followeth in the next words, <hi>After two dayes hee will reuiue vs, in the third day he will raiſe vs vp:</hi> that is, if wee ſeeke him early, he will ſoone ceaſe his plagues; as he ceaſed this generall peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence after the terme of two dayes in the time of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> and as he moderated in like manner the violent rage of the <hi>Pariſian</hi> maſſacre, in which within three dayes ſpace there fell ten thouſand as it were on our right hands, through the raging crueltie of the Romiſh Catholickes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and yet as the Pſalmiſt hath it, it came not nigh vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:27611:28"/>Let vs goe onward with the Text.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord ſent a Peſtilence vpon Iſrael from the morning euen to the time appointed, and there dyed of the People euen from</hi> Dan <hi>to</hi> Berſheba <hi>ſeuentie thouſand men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Seuentie thouſand men.</hi> Hence I gather that oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Lord God puniſheth ſinfull man in the ſame thing, and in ſome ſort after the ſame kind, in which ſinfull man prouoketh the Lord God.</p>
                  <p>Dauid is a ſpeciall inſtance for proofe of this point, here and elſewhere: elſewhere he vnſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed the ſword againſt <hi>Vriah,</hi> &amp; drew the Lords ſword vpon his owne houſe. <hi>Vriam iniuſto ſed non inulto cruore reſperſit:</hi> the ſhedding of <hi>Vriahs</hi> bloud as 'twas vndeſerued, ſo 'twas not vnreuenged, but was puniſhed in due time, in its owne kind: Here he falleth to numbring of his people, and a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his people fall by the peſtilence: Hee ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth about to vnderſtand the number of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to know the end thereof: And God is about to number his people (as hee did <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> Kingdome) <hi>and to finiſh and make an end of it. Dauid</hi> reckoneth without the Lord. It is the poore mans guiſe (ſaith the Poet) to number his ſmall flocke, <hi>Pauperis eſt numerare pecus:</hi> I am ſure twas great weakeneſſe in <hi>Dauid</hi> to number his great forces, as though by their ſtrength, and by his owne right hand he had gotten his victories, chaſed his enemies, and compaſſed the Crowne of Soueraigntie. Yee may ſet <hi>Dauid</hi> in this act in oppoſition with <hi>Abraham: Abraham</hi> hauing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27611:28"/>
but one Sonne will entruſt him with God, who telleth him, that hee will for a reward of his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience multiplie his ſeed: <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people will relye on their ſtrength, and the Lord ſheweth by this plague that hee can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to nothing: he ſweepeth away vpon a ſuddaine, ſeuentie thouſand men. I ſuppoſe there are few trauellers, who hearken after ſtrange newes, but haue heard of that vulgar report in the Eaſtern parts, (as fabulous I thinke as famous) concerning thoſe vaſt ſtones ſcattered within a ſmall compaſſe, in that warlike monument on the Playnes, of which they tell you, that after you haue once numbred them, if yee number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, yee ſhall faile of your former reckoning; the Deuill it may be increaſeth mens ſuperſtitious and groundleſſe credulitie by deluding the ſight, or dazeling the eye: But in this wonderfull peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, &amp; popular plague, diſperſed in that Eaſterne Iſrael; if <hi>Dauid</hi> had gone to take an account of his warriers after the firſt numbring, he might haue found a wonderfull abatement, threeſcore and ten thouſand fallen off from the number, and felled by the peſtilence within Iſraels confines; God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his pride in not repoſing his alone ſafetie and ſecuritie vnder the meere and mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of his mightie hand. Now beloued, not to reſt the proofe of the doctrine too long vpon <hi>Dauid;</hi> If conſidering this ſeptinarie Decade of Thouſands, deſtroid and decaid in <hi>Dauids</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I ſhould affirme that <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſpecially of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27611:29"/>
God by his numbring, and that God is ſet downe in the Text, puniſhing him in a moſt ſpeciall number; Thoſe who are ſo curious in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing numbers, and haue ſuch a number of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious obſeruations touching the ſeuenth number, terming it with <hi>Ambroſe</hi> a ſacred number, and with <hi>Auguſtin</hi> a number myſtically portending a kind of perfection, might happily befriend me herein: But <hi>Chryſost.</hi> would more iuſtly befoole mee for my labour, who tearmeth this curioſitie a fabling and a deuice of mans braine. God tyeth not himſelfe to numbers, neither ſhould we ſeeke to bring him to it by our abſtruſe obſeruations, and ſchoole-quiddities. <hi>Ne ſutor vltra crepidam,</hi> Wee may not thinke (if I may ſo ſpeake) to fit him with the ſeauens, who filleth heauen and earth, making the one his throne, and the other his footſtoole. Twas chiefly for curioſitie of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that ſo many fell of the peſtilence in the Text. Much better had it beene for <hi>Dauid</hi> (and ſo twere for vs in this caſe) inſtead of ſuch a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and needleſſe numbring, ſhortning the dayes and haſtning the deaths of thouſands, to haue deſired (as elſe where he doth) <hi>that God would teach him to number his dayes; and ſo to apply himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wiſedome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All Hiſtories diuine and humane, are ſo full of proofes for the confirming, and illuſtrating of my doctrine, that me thinkes I delight to dwell longer vpon it, then ordinarily I vſe to doe vpon other Doctrines. How memorably hath Gods
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27611:29"/>
hand puniſhed notoriouſly ſinfull acts in their owne kind in all Ages? Doe <hi>Nabab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> prouoke and incenſe the Lord with <hi>ſtrange In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe;</hi> God puniſheth them with <hi>ſtrange fire.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10 1.2.</note> Are the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> not contented with the Lords feeding?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.</note> hee maketh them leaue their carkaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes where they luſted after fleſh. Doe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Ieruſalem offer Incenſe to the Hoast of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen on the tops of their houſes? Ier.</hi> 19.13. <hi>The Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans ſhall come and ſet fire on that Citie, and burne it together with thoſe houſes, Chap.</hi> 22.29. Doe the <hi>Ammonites ſacrifice their children to Molech their Idoll?</hi> themſelues are forced <hi>to paſſe through the Brick-kilne in all their Cities,</hi> 2. <hi>Samuel</hi> 12.31. Doth that cut-finger <hi>Adonibezek</hi> make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſport with mangling the hands, and feete of captiue Kings? the Lord maketh him, when hee is taken captiue, to beſhrew his fingers for it, by dipping them in the ſame bloudy diſh, and ſeruing him with the ſame, ſawce, <hi>Iudges</hi> 1. Doe the ſtiffe-necked <hi>Iewes crucifie Chriſt</hi> at the time of the preparation of their Paſſeouer, It ſeemed good vnto the moſt iuſt God, that <hi>Titus</hi> ſhould plant his ſiege before <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> at the time in which the <hi>Iewes</hi> were aſſembled to celebrate that Feaſt, in which ſiege he alſo crucified diuers thouſands of them before the walls of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> reporteth. Doth the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſet fire vnto Gods faithfull witneſſes? What ſaith hee, who calleth himſelfe <hi>the faithfull and true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Apoc.</hi> 3.14. Hee acquainteth Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27611:30"/>
                     <hi>ſhe ſhall bee burnt with fire, Apoc.</hi> 18.8. Doth ſhee caſt the Saints of God aliue into the fire? <hi>ſhee</hi> her ſelfe <hi>ſhall bee caſt aliue into a Lake of fire burning with Brimſtone. Apoc.</hi> 19.20. Doth <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, King of <hi>England,</hi> burne with the vnnaturall luſts of <hi>So dome?</hi> Gods juſtice ſuffereth his vnnaturall Subiects to depriue him of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigntie, and to force a hot burning Spit tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his fundament, into his entrailes. Doth <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, King of <hi>France,</hi> proteſt that with his own eyes, he will ſee a Proteſtant burnt to aſhes? See how in a iuſt Retributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at a Iuſt or Tourney, the ſplinter of a Speare paſſeth through the ſight of his Beauer, pierceth thorow his Eye, periſheth his Braine, and procureth his death. Doth <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Sixt, Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> prepare a cup of Poyſon for his Cardinals, that by deſtroying their perſons he might enioy what they poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? himſelfe vnawares is made the firſt taſter, and dieth of his owne drench. Doth bloudie <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> deferre his Dinner vpon a greedie and bloudie deſire of hearing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine newes from <hi>Oxford</hi> of ſome Martyrs Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, wherewithall he might make merry? God deferreth not long the kindling of a fire in his body, through the intolerable heate whereof he dieth miſerably, as he liued mercileſſely. Two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examples I find in the <hi>Martyrologie</hi> of our Church, making mainly for the farther proofe (if farther proofes yet need) of my laſt propoſed doctrine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:27611:30"/>I purpoſe to mention no more but thoſe. The firſt is of a certaine Smith who had ſeemed to haue beene ſometimes a zealous profeſſor, but left his Sauiour to ſaue his life, and forſooke the faith for feare of the fire, giuing no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a meſſage brought him from a dying Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, by which hee was exhorted to conſtancie, but this, That he could not burne; What became of him? He was afterwards burnt as he went in to ſaue his goods when his houſe was fired.</p>
                  <p>The other example is of a moſt vnmercifull Churle, who willingly ſuffered a poore diſeaſed Chriſtian Brother, to lye and dye in a ditch neere vnto his houſe, and would by no meanes ſuffer him to be ſheltred in any of his Barnes or Back-houſes, Stalls or Styes. Maſter <hi>Fox</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth him to <hi>Diues</hi> (and well he might) for as <hi>Diues</hi> loued the Dogges which hee kept, more then <hi>Lazarus,</hi> which lay at his gates; fed them, but cared not though he ſterued: ſo this wicked wretch would not afford ſo much as a Dogge-kennell to that diſtreſſed creature: Now marke the miſerable end of this Miſer, not long after, he was found in a Ditch, not farre from that in which he left his poore Brother, not only dead, but ſticking in the ſtinking puddle of the ditch, GOD puniſhing him in the ſame kind, in which he tranſgreſſed, and returning his reward vpon his owne head, as the Prophet <hi>Obadiah</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
                  <p>Thus yee haue ſeene the Lord meaſuring vnto
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27611:31"/>
men according to their owne meaſure, that hee may be memorably knowne by the iudgements which he executeth. Yee haue ſeene him follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men cloſe by the heeles in their owne wayes, to ſhew in deſpight of all cauils, that his wayes are equall and his iudgements iuſt. Yee haue ſeene the fat Buls of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> beaſtly and bloudie men, frying in their owne torments, like <hi>Perillus</hi> in his brazen Bull, that they might know their tortures to be (as a Heathen ſpeaketh) <hi>Indigna paſsis Autoribus digniſsima,</hi> vnworthy of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs who indured them, worthy of the Authours who inuented them.</p>
                  <p>It is high time to wind vp the threed of my ſpeech in a word of application. Doth the Lord then, vſually confound ſinfull men in their owne proiects, caſt them in their owne play, &amp; as it were pay them in their own coine? Beware we then that we willingly ſin in no caſe, ſith God can puniſh vs in the ſame kinde. If wee haue ſinned, let vs ſoone iudge our ſelues, leaſt hee ſuddenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs. Let vs weepe for ſorrow, and bluſh for ſhame, leſt he make vs bleed to death. O ler vs not proceed in ſinne, leaſt we giue him a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne by which he may puniſh vs.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond place, let vs conſider how wee haue dealt with God, when wee caſt with our ſelues, and ſeeme to wonder why he ſhould thus and thus deale with vs. His iudgements are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes iuſt, and ſometime wee may ſee them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly marked out vnto vs, with the character
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27611:31"/>
of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> on. He ſuffering vs to pleaſe our ſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeciall ſinne, till it procureth a ſpeciall iudgement proportionable thereunto: as <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creon</hi> the Poet ſo long fell to his wine, till at laſt he was choaked with the kernell of a Grape.</p>
                  <p>Let vs beloued conferre Gods workes with ours and ſee how iuſtly he hath proceeded againſt vs in many inſtances, or may at leaſt, whenſoeuer his abuſed patience ſhall diſdaine any longer to leaue our prouocations vnpuniſhed.</p>
                  <p>If the corrupt Magiſtrate ſhall ſpare to execute Gods iudgement on notorious offenders, is it not iuſt with God to powre downe iudgements on his owne head? If hee deny patronage to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, depriuing the Orphan of his due, and put him by his portion, what can hee expect but that the Lord ſhould alſo put him out of his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</p>
                  <p>If the ſacrilegious perſon, and Symoniacall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron ſhall prey vpon God, by pilling his Church, ſhall he not pull downe Gods plagues vpon his owne houſe?</p>
                  <p>If the ſuperſtitious perſon ſhall adde vnto Gods Word out of mans inuentions ſhall not the Lord adde vnto him the plagues which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his Booke?</p>
                  <p>If the Swearer ſhall as it were teare the Name of God with his teeth; ſhall not <hi>the Lords curſe enter into his houſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>rent the timber from the ſtones, and conſume both together?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we take away ought by Extortions, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27611:32"/>
exactions, and will not reſtore; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in iuſtice depriue vs of his bleſſings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtore them alſo?</p>
                  <p>If wee ſhut our eares at the cry of the poore; wil not God ſhut his eare at the cry of our prayer?</p>
                  <p>If we ſeeke to <hi>Egypt</hi> for helpe, looke for ſhelter from Idolatrous aſſociates; will not the <hi>ſtrength of ſuch Pharaohs be our ſhame, and the trust in ſuch ſhadowes our confuſion? Eſay</hi> 30.3.</p>
                  <p>Let vs conſider theſe things beloued; and is it not time to conſider them, now the Lord ſendeth his meſſengers abroad to call vs to an account. Shall wee ſhut our hearts alwayes againſt him, euen now when he is ready to ſhut our doores vpon vs, and ſeale them vp with his plagues, which waxe ſo hote among vs of this <hi>Countrey,</hi> yea of this <hi>Countie?</hi> God forbid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord giue vs vnderſtanding, and repentant hearts; the Lord turne vs vnto him, and his fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable countenance towards vs: The Lord receiue our Prayers, heare our groanings, and helpe our griefes.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>ANd thus Gentle Reader, I haue communicated vnto thy view theſe precedent pape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> which were penned (for the moſt part) in great want of time, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou are already aduertiſed. Yet are they ſent abroad, without adding, altering, augmenting or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of any materiall paſſage; that ſo they may follow their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall Copy, which (together with another Tract, not yet publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed) found acceptance at the hands of our Dread and Deare So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne. In reſpect of whoſe gracious Aſpect, I haue the more cauſe to preſume of thy fauour, or (if that may not bee obtayned) the leſſe reaſon to eſteeme thy Cenſure.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27611:32"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
